there are several types of caches when
it comes to which blocks can be placed
where in the cache the cache examples we
have seen so far are the fully
associative caches in this type of a
cache any block from memory can be
placed into any line in the cache so if
the cache has room for 16 lines then we
need to search up to 16 tags in order to
find whether the block we are looking
for is actually in the cache the
opposite of that is a direct mapped
cache where for a given block there is
exactly one place in the cache where
that block can go that means that we
only need to check one line in the cache
if it contains that block because that's
the only line where it can possibly be
different blocks of course we'll still
be able to map to different lines but a
particular block can only go into one
place in the cache and then of course
there is the middle ground between them
which is called a set associative cache
where there are n lines where a block
can be now n typically will be larger
than one and smaller than the total
number of lines in the cache so we can
really view the direct mapped cache as a
case of a set associative cache where n
is one and the fully associative cache
is an extreme case of a set associative
cache where n is equal to the number of
lines in the cache but what we normally
call a set associative cache has a
relatively small and compared to the
number of blocks in that cache yet that
and typically is 2 4 or 8 so it's larger
than 1 now let's look at each of these
types of caches